Guide to the Tamiment Institute Records TAM.007.004
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Institute Records
1935-1990s
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Institute
People's Educational Camp Society
TAM.007.004
15.5 Linear Feet in 11 manuscript boxes, 11 record cartons, and one folder in one shared box.
The Tamiment Institute was founded in 1935 as the educational arm of the People's Educational Camp Society (PECS), which owned and operated Camp Tamiment, an educational and recreational summer resort (originally) for socialists and their families near Bushkill, in Pennsylvania's Pocono Mountains. The Institute organized lectures, conferences and seminars, essay contests, and book awards at the Camp and in New York City. The Collection contains clippings, correspondence, conference and seminar papers, essays, programs, administrative and financial records, and photographs.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Tamiment Institute was founded in 1935 as the educational arm of the People's Educational Camp Society (PECS), which owned and operated Camp Tamiment, originally a resort for socialists. The Institute organized lectures, an annual conference (1930s-40s) that focused on labor, industrial relations and related issues, seminars, an annual essay contest for college students, an annual book award (beginning in 1950), and concerts. These activities took place at the Camp and in New York City. The seminars featured prominent liberal and social-democratic intellectuals of the day, and were jointly sponsored with Daedalus, the journal of the American Academy of the Arts and Sciences, from 1958 to 1962. Topics included the Cold War, the city, and mass culture. Upon the 1956 closure and absorption of the Rand School of Social Science (a New York City school for workers and socialists, with close ties with the American socialist movement, founded in 1906) by PECS, the Institute undertook the reorganization of the Rand School's Meyer London Memorial Library, reopened in 1957 as the Tamiment Institute Library, which it then donated it to New York University in 1963. In 1960 the Institute established the quarterly periodical Labor History. The Institute also published the New Leader, successor to the New York Call.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
The records are organized into three series:
I. Records
II. Photographs
III. Addendum: Administrative and Financial Records and Correspondence (Unprocessed)
Folders are arranged in alphabetical order by title within the processed portion of the collection; unprocessed materials have not been arranged by archivist.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
People's Educational Camp Society and Camp Tamiment (Tamiment 007.3)
Scope and Contents
Contains correspondence, documents, and a small number of photographs relating to the Tamiment Institute's various activities, including its annual conferences, book awards, and essay contest for college students. The collection also includes adminstrative and financial records for the Institute.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the People's Educational Camp Society, 1963. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1963.003, 1963.011, and 2010.103.
A List of Donations Made by Robert D. Bloom in Memory of Louis P. Goldberg was found in the repository. The accession number associated with this material is 2014.047.
Custodial History
The Tamiment Institute Records were transferred to New York University in 1963 by the People's Educational Camp Society (later renamed the Tamiment Institute), as part of a larger transfer of records of the Rand School of Social Science and of organizations associated with the founding and maintenance of the School (including the American Socialist Society, The Society of the Commonwealth Center, and the People's Educational Camp Society) as well as the contents of the School's library, the Meyer London Memorial Library. Additional records were donated in later years, whose likely source is the New York City law firm of Vladeck, Waldman, Elias & Engelhard.
A List of Donations Made by Robert D. Bloom in Memory of Louis P. Goldberg was found in the repository. The accession number associated with this material is 2014.047.
Adult education |z Pennsylvania.; Socialism -- United States.; Black-and-white photographs.; Liberalism |z United States; Liberals |z United States.; Summer resorts -- Pennsylvania.; Socialists -- United States.; Handlin, Oscar, 1915-; Berenson, Bernard, 1865-1959; Josephson, Ben, 1895-1980; Erikson, Erik H. (Erik Homburger), 1902-1994; Bettelheim, Bruno; Morgenthau, Hans J. (Hans Joachim), 1904-1980; Nagel, Ernest, 1901-1985; Mailly, Bertha Howell -- |v Correspondence; Hook, Sidney, 1902-1989; Rosten, Leo Calvin, 1908-1997; Tamiment Institute; Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971; Parsons, Talcott, 1902-1979; Camp Tamiment (Pa.); Jacobs, Norman; People's Educational Camp Society; Blaker, Ben; Bohn, William E.; People's Educational Camp Society
- Series I: Records, 1935-1972
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I contains correspondence relating to the Tamiment Institute's various activities, including its annual conferences, notably one that established the journal Labor History, transcripts of conference and seminar papers, entries from the annual essay contest for college students, material relating to the institute's annual book awards, brochures and programs, clippings, and administrative and financial records. The principal correspondents are the successive educational directors of the Tamiment Institute: William E. Bohn, Ben Blaker, and Norman Jacobs, whose correspondence includes exchanges with prominent intellectuals, labor leaders and educators, socialists, journalists, and political figures, mostly concerning their possible or actual participation in Institute-sponsored events and activities. There is also some correspondence of successive Camp Tamiment Directors Bertha Mailly and Ben Josephson, as well as correspondence related to the 50th Anniversary of the New Leader. Conference/seminar papers include those by Bernard Berenson, Bruno Bettelheim, Erik Erikson, Oscar Handlin, Sidney Hook, Hans J. Morgenthau, Ernest Nagel, Reinhold Niebuhr, Talcott Parsons, and Leo Rosten.
  - Bohn, William E.: "A Short Snappy Biography" (typescript), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book Award (3rd: 1952) (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - Book Award (4th: 1953), 192-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Book Award (5th: 1954), 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book Award (6th: 1955), 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book Award (7th: 1956) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Book Award (8th: 1957) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Book Award (9th: 1958) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Camp Tamiment: Brochures, 1958-1960 (Box 1a, Folder 1)
  - Camp Tamiment Mortgage: Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1a, Folder 2)
  - Camp Tamiment Town Meeting Series, 1941 (Box 1a, Folder 3)
  - Chamber Music Festivals: Pamphlets and Posters, 1953-1957 (Box 1a, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1941-1942, 1950 (Box 1a, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1926, 1947-1948 (Box 1a, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1a, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1951, 1956 (Box 1a, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Waldman & Waldman, Attorney, 1954 (Box 1a, Folder 9)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on Mass Culture, 1959 (Box 1a, Folder 10)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on Mass Culture: Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on Mass Culture: Correspondence, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on Mass Culture: Minutes, 1959 Jun (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on Mass Culture: Papers, 1959 Mar (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on Mass Culture: Papers, Drafts, 1959 Jun (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on Mass Culture: Related Magazines and Pamphlets, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on the Metropolis: Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on the Metropolis: Minutes, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on the Metropolis: Papers, Drafts, 1960 Jun (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on Youth: Correspondence, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on Youth: Correspondence, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on Youth: Papers, Drafts, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on United States Foreign Policy, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Daedalus and Tamiment Institute Seminar on United States Foreign Policy: Draft Texts, 1962 May (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Essay Contest (1st), 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Essay Contest (1st) Correspondence Regarding Eligibility and Certification of Contestants, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Essay Contest (1st) Essays, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Essay Contest (1st) Evaluation Material, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Essay Contest (1st) Log, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Essay Contest (2nd), 1947 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Essay Contest (2nd) Correspondence: Postcards, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Essay Contest (2nd) Correspondence Relating To Information And Entry-Blanks, 1947 Jan-1947 Feb (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Essay Contest (2nd) Correspondence Relating To Information And Entry-Blanks, 1948 Jan (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Essay Contest (2nd) Correspondence Relating To Information And Entry-Blanks, 1948 Feb (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Essay Contest (2nd) Correspondence Relating To Information And Entry-Blanks, 1948 Mar-1948 Apr (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Essay Contest (2nd) Correspondence Relating To Information And Entry-Blanks, 1948 May-1948 Dec (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Essay Contest (2nd) Evaluation Materials, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Essay Contest (2nd) Log, 1947-1948 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Essay Contest (2nd) Non-Prize Winning Essays/1, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Essay Contest (2nd) Non-Prize Winning Essays/2, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Essay Contest (2nd) Prize Winning Essays, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Essay Contest (2nd) Reports, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Essay Contest (4th) Correspondence, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Essay Contests: Bulletins and Publicity Materials, 1946-1948 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Financial, 1972-1974 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Forum on Communism in the Twentieth Century, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 2a)
  - Forum on Marxism Correspondence, 1958 Nov-1959 Mar (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Forum on American Foreign Policy – Minutes, 1958 Feb 26 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Josephson, Ben Yearbook (Calendar), 1963 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Labor Archives of the Tamiment Library at NYU: Correspondence, 1964-1968 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Labor History Conference: Correspondence, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Labor History: Correspondence, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Labor History: Correspondence, 1959-1962 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Lecture Series: Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Lecture Series: Correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Lee, Algernon: Life Insurance Policy – Correspondence, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Lee, Algernon: Obituaries, 1954 Jan (Box 8, Folder 3a)
  - List of Donations Made by Robert D. Bloom in Memory of Louis P. Goldberg, circa 1938 (Box Tamiment Shared MS002)
  - Meyer London Memorial Library, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - National Labor Conference (1st), 1935 (Box 8, Folder 4a)
  - National Labor Conference (2nd), 1936 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - New Leader: Loan to 50th Anniversary of, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Rand School: Winter Ball, 1921 (Box 8, Folder 6a)
  - Seminar on Education: Clippings, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Seminar on Education: Correspondence, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 7a)
  - Seminar on Education – Papers: Arthur Bestor, Douglas Bush, John Childs, Sidney Hook, Hans J. Morgenthau, 1958 Jun (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Seminar on Education: Partial Transcript, 1958 Jun (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - String Quartet Composition Award: Correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - String Quartet Composition Award: Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (4th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (5th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1938 Sep-1939 Jul (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (6th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1940 Apr-1940 May (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (6th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1940 May-1940 Jun (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (7th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1941 Feb-1941 Jun 19 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (7th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1941 Jun 20-1941 Jun 27 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (8th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1942 Mar-1942 Jul (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (9th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1943 May-1943 Jul (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (9th) – Labor Union Attendance: Correspondence and Other Materials, 1943 May-1943 Jun (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (10th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1944 Apr-1944 Aug (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (10th) – Labor Union Attendance: Correspondence and Other Materials, 1944 Mar-1944 Aug (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (11th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1945 May-1945 Jul (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (12th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1946 Apr-1946 Jun (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (12th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1946 Jun 20-1946 Jun 28 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (13th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1947 Jun 6-1947 Jun 24 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (14th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1948 Apr-1948 May (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference (14th): Correspondence and Other Materials, 1948 Jun (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Tamiment Institute Library: Reports, 1957-1959 (Box 10, Folder 7a)
  - Tamiment Institute Publications, Requests for, Invoices, etc., 1955-1961 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - The Sandpiper (Sandyville School children's newsletter), 1935 (Box 10, Folder 8a)
  - Vladeck, Baruch Charney Biography: Grant to Franklin Jonas, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Series II. Photographs, 1950-1958, undated
  Series II consists of black and white photographs that include images of the Tamiment Institute's annual book award ceremonies, of 1950 (to Rupert Hughes for his fictionalized biography of Samuel Gompers "The Giant Awakes"), 1951 (to Ethel Waters, for her autobiography, "His Eye Is On The Sparrow), 1953 (Carl Sandberg, for "Always the Young Strangers"), and 1958 (to John Kenneth Galbraith for "The Affluent Society"), at Camp Tamiment in Bushkill, Pennsylvania and at the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel in New York City. Besides the authors being honored, photographs include Marx Lewis, Daniel Bell, Harry Laidler, Ben Josephson, and Eugene Lyons. Some were shot by Camp Tamiment photographer "Snappy" Lewis Goren. There are also shots of of unidentified lectures or seminars and classical music performances at Camp Tamiment circa the 1950s.
  - Tamiment Institute - Photographs, 1950-1958 (Box Tamiment Shared A006, Folder 1)
  - Loose photograph of Perry Como and child, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 018, Folder 19)
- Series III. Addendum: Administrative and Financial Records and Correspondence (Unprocessed), 1970s-1990s, undated
  Series III consists of administrative and financial records, and correspondence from 1970s through the 1990s.
  - Administrative Records 1, undated (Box 11)
  - Administrative Records 2, undated (Box 12)
  - Administrative Records 3, undated (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1970s-1990s (Box 14)
  - Financial Records 1, undated (Box 15)
  - Financial Records 2, undated (Box 16)
  - Financial Records 3, undated (Box 17)
  - Financial Records 4, undated (Box 18)
  - Financial Records 5, undated (Box 19)
  - Financial Records 6, undated (Box 20)
  - Financial Records 7, undated (Box 21)